Guide to the N. Scott Momaday Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Papers, 1788-2012; 1950s-2012
  - Invitation to the 8th annual Arts and Crafts show at Jemez Day School, 1956; Correspondence b/w Natachee and Houghton Mifflin Company, 1971; Letters to Natachee S. Momaday 1960-1968; Airline ticket stubs from a trip Natachee took to New York, 1972; Correspondence b/w Natachee and the Kayenta Elementary School and the Uintah School District, 1972; and correspondence to presses, circa 1970s (Box 18)
  - Journal entries? From Santa Fe and San Francisco; Review of The Way to Rainy Mountain by Janet Lewis; Transcribed interview with NSM with the University of California, 1966; Review of House Made of Dawn by John Ridland, 1968; "A Checklist of Bronteana: 1948-60" by NSM 1960; Press coverage of NSM The Way to Rainy Mountain, circa 1960s (Box 18)
  - Envelope of NSM articles that appeared in Viva Santa Fe in the 1960s and 1970s, circa 1960s (Box 18)
  - Newspaper clippings about: Haskell reunion; Reviews of The Names; Announcement of a book and author luncheon at St. James College in Santa Fe, NSM listed as a speaker, November 1969; Various news clippings on NSM; "The Story of the Arrowmaker" by NSM; Letters to Al and Natachee S. Momaday from NSM 1970-71; Letter to NSM from the Law Offices of Stewart L. Udall, 1969; postcards; Oklahomans for Indian Opportunity, Annual Report 1969-70; Article in the Albuquerque Area Education Profile about Al Momaday and NSM receiving honorary degrees from Lawrence University in Wisconsin, circa 1960s (Box 18)
  - Albuquerque Journal article on Natachee S. Momaday and Owl in the Cedar Tree Sept. 12, 1965, circa 1960s (Box 18)
  - Various newspaper clippings on Natachee, Al and NSM 1970-80s, circa 1970s (Box 18)
  - Miscellaneous news clippings; Article on NSM by Roger Dickinson-Brown "The Art and Importance of NSM"; Letters to an from Natachee in the 1960s; Article on Natachee in the Theta State News, 1965; Letters and cards to and from Natachee 1960s, circa 1960s (Box 18)
  - Autry National Center "Rendezvous" Old West Fest and Third Annual Gathering of Cowboy Culture, Music, and Poetry program, auction catalog, and cards. NSM received the Humanities Prize., undated (Box 18)
  - List of Wheelwright Museum Board of Trustees, Sept. 1998, circa 1990s (Box 18)
  - A Centennial Tribute to Louis Leakey 1903-2003: The Leakey Foundation Planning Document NSM an advisor to the board; The 2002 Leakey Foundation Annual Meeting and Symposium booklet with a letter to trustees and advisors; National Geographic August 2002, circa 2000s (Box 18)
  - L.S.B. Leakey Foundation April Board Meeting folder, April 25, 2003 with letters attached; L.S.B. Leakey Foundation December Board Meeting folder, December 6, 2002., circa 2000s (Box 18)
  - Grand Canyon Trust correspondence memorandums, 1999; Grand Canyon Trust Board of Trustees Meeting, Nov. 5, 1999 Springdale, Utah copy for NSM; Card noting the donation of an original painting "In All Its Glory" to the trust by the artist, Curt Walters with a certificate of authenticity; Grand Canyon Trust Board of Trustees Meeting, Flagstaff, AZ, Sept. 28, 2000 copy for NSM, circa 2000s (Box 18)
  - Manuscript of "Set" by NSM, undated (Box 18)
  - "Telling Stories Out of School: Remembering the Carlisle Indian Industrial School, 1879-1918" A dissertation by Genevieve Bell, June 1998, circa 1990s (Box 19)
  - Folder labeled: "Sign Language: Photographs by Skeet McAuley" from the Aperture Foundation. NSM agreed to write a forward for the book and this is the background and research with information on the structure of the book and the photographs and description of each photo, undated (Box 19)
  - The Arts section of the Albuquerque Journal with artwork by NSM, 1989; Letter from the United State Information Agency regarding NSM trip to Yugoslavia and Finland, 1989; Letter to Bobby, 1990; Photocopy of a excerpt from House Made of Dawn; Misc. correspondence, 1980s; Letter from Celia Eckhardt; Copy of information on NSM work; Contract with the Southeastern Louisiana University to be a Scholar-In-Residence April, 1985., circa 1980s (Box 19)
  - Letter from the Library of Congress regarding a reading by NSM on March 27, 1989; Letter from Doubleday publishing about a author questionnaire with three copies of the questionnaire filled out by NSM, 1989; Christmas Eve poem, My Precious Place poem; Cards to NSM; Letter from David Weber about The Names, 1989; Itinerary and letter for a trip to California State University, Chico, 1989; Correspondence regarding an award from the Friends of the Scottsdale Library, 1988; Correspondence from the University of Arizona regarding the Regents Professor Support Fund, 1988; Calendar of class meetings, 1989; Payment stub from the University of Wisconsin for the Winds of Change project, 1989; Legal agreements regarding The Ancient Child Permissions to use citations in books, 1989; Marilyn Butler Fine Art schedule, 1989, NSM presenter, Copy of "The Southwest" by NSM; Correspondence about prizes, circa 1980s (Box 19)
  - Travel guide to France; Letter from Jill Momaday to NSM, 1989; Letter from the Rutherford B. Hayes Presidential center regarding NSM participation in a conference; Letters from the Friends of the Scottsdale Public Library; Information on the speakers series at the University of New Mexico. 1989; various invitations to speak; Personal letters and correspondence; "The Free Sounds of the Joik in Writing" by Harald Gaski; Agreements for presentations, 1989; Personal birthday cards, "The Becoming of the Native: Man in America Before Columbus"; Agreements with Doubleday about The Ancient Child 1989; Correspondence with Rydal Press; "From Head to Toe with Native American Running" by John Aronson with NSM; Library of Congress Information Bulletin Vol. 48, No. 16 April 17, 1989 with NSM On cover; Department on English self-study committees, 1988-89; Empty photo album; Misc. correspondence, circa 1980s (Box 19)
  - Schedule of Classes for University of Arizona, Fall 1989; Note announcing that Mr. Hans-Peter Rodenberg will visit NSM on April/May; Handwritten list of art, University of Arizona; letter from California Cooper; "A Dark, Indifferent Rage: The Proposal of a Novel" by NSM; Letters from his daughters; Writings by Christopher Logue; Letter "Dear Professor Martin" no signature, 1982; Correspondence c. 1983, circa 1980s (Box 19)
  - Letters and correpondence c. 1983; Royalty statements; personal and business correspondence, c. 1983; Information on the Wester Lit. Assoc. meeting in St. Paul, 1983; Information on a joint project between the Museum of Natural History and the Museum of the American Indian; Agreement for NSM participation in "The Ancient Americans: Infinite voyage"; Letters about a createive writing project and Stanford Univ. Libraries, 1988; Letter recognizing NSM as a Regents Professor, 1988; Personal notes to NSM and Regina; Letter from Univ. of Nebraska; Letter from the Modern Language Association informing NSM that they will use the his drawing "Mammedaty" on the cover of The Way to Rainy Mountain, 1988; Letter from Frederick Hoxie regarding the intro to America in 1492 and "Tales from the Center of the Universe", 1988 with draft; pictures of a woman and a dog; Letter about the publication of Elements of Literature; Agreement to write an article for National Geographic, 1988; Nomination letter by NSM supporting Shahrokh Rezvani; Royalty statements from University of Arizona, circa 1980s (Box 19)
  - Booklet in German on NSM, 1986; dust jacket to Approaches to Teaching Momaday's: The Way to Rainy Mountain, by Kenneth M. Roemer; "Rainy Mountain" a sixty-minute Dramatic/Documentary Film by WFYI, Indianapolis; Letter from the Stanford Magazine asking NSM to write a piece for the 100 anniversary issue; Various personal correspondence, 1990; Note from New York Newsday regarding NSM review of Linda Hogan's Mean Spirit; NSM review of Mean Spirit; Various copies of letters from NSM to others both personal and business related, 1990, Statement from the BIA Individual Indian Monies; Many letters to Barbara Glenn Momaday, 1990, circa 1990s (Box 19)
  - Letters to Barbara, 1990; personal correspondence; Moving receipts, 1990; "Carnegie, Oklahoma, 1919", "Touch", "Hill Country Sonnet in Dialogue", "Lawrence Ranch" poems by NSM; Various personal correspondence 1990; Employment agreement from Fred Hoxie and the Newberry Library; Letter from the Smithsonian Institution regarding a presentation by NSM; Agreement with The Wendy Weil Agency regarding the publication of A Dark, Indifferent Rage, 1989; Information of the Rainy Mountain Meeting in Santa Fe, 1990, circa 1990s (Box 19)
  - Letter from Yvonne Kauger in response to NSM letter, 1990; Letter from Alexandr Vaschenko, 1990; Drawing my Lore; Letter regarding NSM serving as a member of the 1991 Pulitzer Prize Fiction Jury; Agreement of The Ancient Child 1990; Photocopies of newspaper stories on NSM; "Zeitschrift der Gesellschaft fur Kanada-Studerien" by Kurt Jurgensen and Hans-Josef Niederehe; Letter regarding funds adjustments from the University of Arizona A, 1987; Appendix and chronology of Way to Rainy Mountain; "Meeting a Bear" by David Wagoner; Letter from University of Arizona president asking NSM to give the commencement address, 1987; Royalty statements from Harper & Row", circa 1980s (Box 19)
  - Personal correspondence; Letter from Daniet Shea at Washington University regarding sections of classes, 1984; "The Making of a Hopi; McDougal, Littell & Company asking for a photo of NSM, 1987; Calendar of class meetings, 1987; Story on Tally Richards; German articles; Publishing Agreements with James R. Hepworth for Man Made of Words; Observations and Essays, 1987; Travel expense Report; Contract to visit students at Maricopa Community college; Information on the Columbian Quincentenary and America in 1492, 1987; Drafts and agreements of America in 1492, circa 1980s (Box 19)
  - Correspondence, letters and agreements, c. 1984, circa 1980s (Box 19)
  - "Reporter-10" by NSM 1967 with a note from Nore L. Magid at The Reporter Dec. 4 1967 in original mailing envelope; Portraits on NSM in a San Francisco Commercial Photography undated; negative strips from what appears to be photographs of a trip abroad, circa 1960s (Box 19)
  - 5x7 color photographic prints labeled: Near Lake Hefner, March 1980; "This tree at Lake Hefner is one that Hokusai might have drawn" March 1980; North of Oklahoma City; A Different view, March 1980; Between Oklahoma City and Edmond, March 1980; Between Oklahoma City and Edmond, March 1980; North of Oklahoma City, March 1980; "I am fond of this one. It's where my father and I walked near Edmond Oklahoma, March 1980., circa 1980s (Box 19)
  - Notebook with translations into Russian. Appears to be NSM study guide for learning the language, undated (Box 19)
  - Spiral notebook with musings and prose handwritten by NSM, undated (Box 19)
  - Spiral notebook with research notes on tribes across the United states., undated (Box 19)
  - Request for a refund of Member's Retirement from the New Mexico Educational Retirement Board 1973; Note that NSM sabbatical leave was approved, 1970; Letter to NSM from Peter Francis Nabokov asking for a recommendation letter with his resume; Photocopy of the publication "Frederick Goddard Tuckerman's "The Cricket": An Introductory Note"; Thomas Jefferson's Ten Rules, circa 1970s (Box 19)
  - Current Biography Vol. 34, Num. 4, April 1973 with no evidence of a story on the Momadays; "Pskov-Maiden: An Opera by Rimskiy-Korsakov in a mailing envelope; Handwritten note in red ink; Syllabus for a class "thinking in Prose and Verse" taught by Dr. Jeffrey Goodman, 1981; Note to NSM from unknown regarding poems, 1981, circa 1970s (Box 19)
  - Map of Amherst, MA; Handwritten notes about Amherst; typed notes on Emily Dickinson, 1966; handwritten notes on Emily Dickinson, 1966, circa 1960s (Box 19)
  - Handwritten prose on a yellow notebook; handwritten speech; NSM review of A History of the Indians of the United States by Angie Debo; Misc. typed pages; "Green" by William Jay Smith, undated (Box 19)
  - "The Bostonians: Characterization and Curiosity" by NSM for Mr. Howe's English 381a, 1961, circa 1960s (Box 19)
  - Writing piece by NSM "Bring on the Indians" c.1960s, circa 1960s (Box 19)
  - Correspondence with Victor Gollancz, LTD regarding the publication of House Made of Dawn 1968, circa 1960s (Box 19)
  - Draft of an essay "Man Made of Words" to the New York times book editor, 1969 with hand written corrections and correspondence with the press., circa 1960s (Box 19)
  - Legal contracts for House Made of Dawn screenplay., undated (Box 19)
  - Drawing by NSM, undated (Box 20)
  - Draft manuscript of The Way to Rainy Mountain with handwritten notes., undated (Box 20)
  - Spiral notebook dated 1967 with handwritten notes and page numbers. Appears to be reference numbers, circa 1960s (Box 20)
  - Spiral notebook dated 1967 with handwritten notes and page numbers. Appears to be reference numbers, circa 1960s (Box 20)
  - Black and white portraits of NSM one framed the other loose, undated (Box 20)
  - Spiral bound draft manuscript of The Ancient Child, undated (Box 20)
  - Numerous letters from Bob Nelson c. 1960-1963 with the envelopes, circa 1960s (Box 20)
  - Painted piece of wood (from daughter?); Photographs from a trip abroad (Russia?), undated (Box 20)
    Audiocassette "Man Made of Words NS Momaday" removed to Box 147.
  - Blue Binder with "Tsoai-Talee: Conversations with NSM" Edited with an introduction, topical essays, and an afterward by Charles L. Woodard`, undated (Box 20)
  - Manuscript of The Man Made of Words by NSM with editors' notes and a letter From Andre Miller of St. Martin's Press regarding the manuscript dated June 23, 1998, circa 1990s (Box 20)
  - Multiple copies of the same poem without a title by NSM; An agreement with Native Peoples Magazine for "A Christmas Orange" by NSM, 2003., circa 2000s (Box 20)
  - Two copies of a short story version of Children of the Sun: A Story and Play by NSM, undated (Box 20)
  - Two copies of the manuscript for The Indolent Boys by NSM, undated (Box 20)
  - Numerous copies of NSM resume and brief bios of the author c. 1993, circa 1990s (Box 20)
  - Brief Biographies of NSM; NSM letter "To Whom it May Concern" regarding fees for public lectures and presentations; Numerous blank sheets of NSM fax letterhead, undated (Box 20)
  - NSM Bios, undated (Box 20)
  - Manuscript of Earth, Pray My Days: New and Selected Poems by NSM, undated (Box 20)
  - Manuscript of The Bear-God Dialogues by NSM, undated (Box 20)
  - Original manuscript of the Indolent Boys by NSM, undated (Box 20)
  - Contract with St. Martin's Press, February 17, 1995 for The Storyteller and His Art; Correspondence with St. Martin's Press regarding the publication of The Man Made of Word on an electronic book reader, Feb. 1999, circa 1990s (Box 20)
  - Manuscript of The Bear-God Dialogues by NSM; Correspondence with St/ Martin's Press regarding the publication of The Bear-God Dialogues 1998-1999; Manuscript of The Bear-God Dialogues with editors' notes., circa 1990s (Box 20)
  - Drafts of poems and dialogues for In the Bear's House by NSM, circa 1990s (Box 20)
  - Brochure for the Museum of Contemporary Religious Art, St. Louis University,; Article from the St Louis Post-Dispatch "Everyday" by Jane Henderson entitled" American Indian Writer Will Receive the St. Louis Literary Award, dated October 2000; Program for the Associates of St. Louis University Libraries, Inc. honoring of Chinua Achebe, 1999; Correspondence regarding the trip to St. Louis, 2000, circa 1990s (Box 22)
  - Letter from Elizabeth Sackler of the American Indian Ritual Object Repatriation Foundation regarding fundraising activities, 2000; Card announcing the NSM and Elizabeth Sackler are hosting an Open House Auction, Nov. 2008; Receipts of payment for NSM travel to the open house, circa 2000s (Box 22)
  - Copy of Children of the Sun with a letter to Roundhouse Theatre about performing a reading of the play, 2000, circa 2000s (Box 22)
  - Paperwork for class "Native American Oral Tradition" taught by NSM, undated (Box 22)
  - Two copies of The Indolent Boys manuscripts, undated (Box 22)
  - Aleutian Life Forum Sponsorship Information packet. 2005, circa 2000s (Box 22)
  - Five copies of Native Peoples magazine with NSM on the cover with "A Christmas Orange" by NSM on page 44 and a story on NSM on page 45, Nov/Dec 2003, circa 2000s (Box 22)
  - Folder with a review of NSM In the Presence of the Sun Nov, 1992; Two copies of a Booklet from The New Mexico D.H. Lawrence Festival July 16-20, 1980 with NSM listed on page 46, circa 1980s (Box 22)
  - Magazines: New Mexico Jan-Feb 1970 with a story on Al Momaday by Dorothy Dunn on page 36; Natural History 1983 with a review by NSM of Now That the Buffalo's Gone by Alvin M. Josephy, Jr.; Natural History 1990 with a review by NSM of Native Americans: Five Centuries of Changing Images by Patricia Trenton, circa 1980s (Box 22)
  - Two loose copies of "The Strange and True Story of My Life with Billy the Kid" by NSM from American West 1985; American West: Airlines Magazine June 1985, with an article by NSM "Tenure in the Land" on page 21; Three copies of American West: The Land and its People Sept/Oct 1985 with "The Strange and True Story of My Life with Billy the Kid" by NSM on page 54, circa 1980s (Box 22)
  - Two copies of Southwest Profile Jan 1990 with and interview with NSM on page 33; Southwest Profile Sept. 1989 with no indication a Momaday is featured in the volume; Santa Fe Gallery Portfolio 1989, circa 1990s (Box 22)
  - Geo Special: USA Southwest 1989 a German magazine with an article in German on NSM on page 38; Fortune magazine 2001 featuring NSM, circa 2000s (Box 22)
  - Letter from Qawalangin Tribe of Unalaska asking NSM to be a guest speaker with a copy of the Bering Sea and Aleutian Islands by Terry Johnson; Santa Fean August 2005, with a story on NSM on page 230; Ikce Wicasta magazine Winter 2006, with an article that mentions NSM on page 43, circa 2000s (Box 22)
  - Sequoia Centennial Issue, 1987 with a poem "Mogollon Morning" by NSM on page 46, circa 1980s (Box 22)
  - DVD Journey of the Tiglax, undated (Box 22)
  - Invitation to the National Museum of the American Indian Inaugural Exhibition, 1992. with a painting by NSM listed in the auction; Card inviting to an exhibit of NSM work at the Wheelwright Museum of the American Indian, Oct 10 1992; The Canadian Review of American Studies Spring 1980 with an article by H. David Brumble III using NSM work; Packet for City Places conference, 1987 NSM Speaker; Program for the Harvard presentation of the Indolent Boys; Exhibition card from an exhibit of NSM work at LewAllen/Butler Fine Arts, May 5-27, 1989; Program for Rosequist/40 with NSM paintings; Booklet for NSM exhibition in Germany (in German), circa 1980s (Box 22)
  - Miscellaneous business cards and menus and a picture of Natachee, undated (Box 22)
  - Mountain Plains Library Association Literary Contribution Award, 2010 to NSM Award and Letter, circa 2010s (Box 22)
  - Newspapers: The Stanford Observer, Nov. 1973 with a story on NSM on page 2; Albuquerque News, July 23 1980 With a story on NSM; The Stanford Daily with story on NSM on page 3, 1975; Other misc news clippings on NSM, circa 1970s (Box 22)
  - Colors of the Night by NSM Arion Press Broadsides Number Three, 1976, circa 1970s (Box 22)
  - Interview with NSM 1980, circa 1980s (Box 22)
  - Personal correspondence with Camille Adkins including a transcript of an interview with NSM in Tucson, Arizona April, 21 1993., circa 1990s (Box 22)
  - Card from Keith Basso to NSM, 1993, circa 1990s (Box 22)
  - Personal correspondence with John Stevens Berry with a photo of Berry's family, 1992, circa 1990s (Box 22)
  - Personal correspondence with Mary Jane Boscacci, 1992, circa 1990s (Box 22)
  - Letter from NSM to Todd K. Bender, 1993, circa 1990s (Box 22)
  - Correspondence with Linda Bolton, 1994, circa 1990s (Box 22)
  - Postcards, cards and letters from Dick Bridgeman, c. 1997, circa 1990s (Box 22)
  - Correspondence with Gail Bruce and stories about Tom Bee, circa 1990s (Box 22)
  - Correspondence with Scott W. Burgan and information about Kiowa history, circa 1990s (Box 22)
  - Correspondence with Bonnie G. Colby and a proposal regarding Indian Water Rights through the University of Arizona, circa 1990s (Box 22)
  - Letters to Johnetta B. Cole, 1996, circa 1990s (Box 22)
  - Correspondence with Michael Curtis, 1994, circa 1990s (Box 22)
  - Personal correspondence with Vine Deloria, Jr. c. 1994, circa 1990s (Box 22)
  - Letter and card from Valerie T. Diker, undated (Box 22)
  - Booklet "The Cowboy West: 100 Years of Photography" C.M. Russell Museum, Great Falls, Montana, 1992, circa 1990s (Box 22)
  - Personal correspondence with Patty Ewald, 1994, circa 1990s (Box 22)
  - Correspondence with Celia Morris Eckhardt with papers by Eckhardt, c. 1988, circa 1980s (Box 22)
  - Correspondence with Dorene Falk, c. 1994, circa 1990s (Box 22)
  - Correspondence with Dennis Ferrier, 1993, circa 1990s (Box 22)
  - Correspondence with Mirdza Erika Berzins regarding Steven Feld nomination for the MacArthur Fellowship, 1990, circa 1990s (Box 22)
  - Correspondence with Warren Foley, 1992, circa 1990s (Box 22)
  - Correspondence with Joan Fry C. 1988, circa 1980s (Box 22)
  - Correspondence with Barbara Glenn, 1993-1995, circa 1990s (Box 22)
  - Correspondence with Howarth & Smith attorneys at law, 1993, circa 1990s (Box 22)
  - Contract with Doubleday Publishing for and untitled manuscript, 1989, circa 1980s (Box 22)
  - Correspondence Helen Houghton to NSM June 8, 1992, including two photos of NSM on a picnic; Correspondence NSM to Helen Houghton March 21, 1994; Correspondence Helen Houghton to NSM February 1, 1995; Correspondence NSM to Helen Houghton March 7, 1995, circa 1990s (Box 23)
  - Correspondence from NSM to Ruth Hart, July 12, 1994, March 14, 1994, circa 1990s (Box 23)
  - Birth announcement of granddaughter, Shai, from Gerry Hausman, November 9, 1993, circa 1990s (Box 23)
  - Correspondence from Darren Vigil-Gray The Morning Star Foundation, to NSM November 8, 1992; Correspondence from Susan Harjo, The 1992 ALLIANCE to NSM, undated; Correspondence from Susan Harjo to NSM, undated; Correspondence from Susan Harjo to NSM, October 16, 1993, circa 1990s (Box 23)
  - Correspondence to Jim Hepworth from NSM regarding Barbara Glenn's poems, January 27, 1993; Correspondence to NSM from Jim Hepworth regarding publication of Barbara Glenn's poems, March 10, 1993; Correspondence NSM to Jim Hepworth regarding publication of Barbara Glenn's manuscript, March 23, 1993., circa 1990s (Box 23)
  - Correspondence NSM to Hartwig-Isernhagen, March 22, 1994, April 6, 1994, July 9, 1994., circa 1990s (Box 23)
  - Correspondence NSM to John Kincheloe regarding Kiowa photographs, September 8, 1993., circa 1990s (Box 23)
  - Correspondence William Kittredge 1993-1994, circa 1990s (Box 23)
  - Correspondence from Al Kulth, October 1, 1992, circa 1990s (Box 23)
  - Correspondence from Charles Kuralt, July 15, 1993, circa 1990s (Box 23)
  - Correspondence to Patty Limerick, December 1 1996; Two copies of NSM's two pages of writings, circa 1990s (Box 23)
  - Copies of writings of Phyllis Lindsay's writings, undated (Box 23)
  - Correspondence with Lisa Marvel, October 1994-March 1995, circa 1990s (Box 23)
  - Correspondence with Rebecca Mobbs, August 11, 1994, circa 1990s (Box 23)
  - Birthday Card to NSM from Phyllis Lindsay, undated; Correspondence with Phyllis Lindsay 1993-1996., circa 1990s (Box 23)